Presenter:
This evening we’re delighted to welcome Dan Beagle,
who’s just written a book on looking for and finding food in the
wild.
He’s going to tell us everything we need to know about picking wild
mushrooms.
Dan:
Thank you very much.
Well, I need to start by talking about safety.
You really need to know what you’re doing because some mushrooms are extremely
poisonous.
Having said that, once you know what to look for, it’s really worth doing
for the amazing variety of mushrooms available – which you can’t get in the
shops.
But of course, you have to be very careful and that’s why I always
say you should never consume mushrooms picked by friends or neighbours – always remember
that some poisonous mushrooms look very similar to edible ones
and it’s easy for people to get confused.
The other thing to avoid is mushrooms growing beside busy roads for obvious reasons.
But nothing beats the taste of freshly picked mushrooms – don’t forget that the
ones in the shops are often several days old and past their best.
There are certain ideas about wild mushrooms that it’s important to be aware
of.
Don’t listen to people who tell you that it’s only OK to eat mushrooms that are pale
or dull – this is completely untrue.
Some edible mushrooms are bright red, for example.
Personally, I prefer mushrooms cooked but it won’t do you any harm to eat
them uncooked in salads – it’s not necessary to peel them.
Another thing you should remember is that you can’t tell if a mushroom is
safe to eat by its smell – some of the most deadly mushrooms have no smell
and taste quite nice, apparently.
Finally, just because deer or squirrels eat a particular mushroom doesn’t mean that you
can.
Of course, mushroom picking is associated with the countryside but if you haven’t got
a car, your local park can be a great place to start.
There are usually a range of habitats where mushrooms grow, such as playing fields
and wooded areas.
But you need to be there first thing in the morning, as there’s likely
be a lot of competition – not just from people but wildlife too.
The deer often get the best mushrooms in my local park.
If you’re a complete beginner, I wouldn’t recommend going alone
or relying on photos in a book, even the one I’ve written!
There are some really good phone apps for identifying mushrooms,
but you can’t always rely on getting a good signal in the middle of
a wood.
If possible, you should go with a group led by an expert – you’ll stay safe
and learn a lot that way.
Conservation is a really important consideration and you must follow a few basic rules.
You should never pick all the mushrooms in one area – collect only enough
for your own needs.
Be very careful that you don’t trample on young mushrooms or other plants.
And make sure you don’t pick any mushrooms that are endangered
and protected by law.
There’s been a decline in some varieties of wild mushrooms in this part of
the country.
Restaurants are becoming more interested in locally sourced food like wild mushrooms,
but the biggest problem is that so many new houses have been built in
this area in the last ten years.
And more water is being taken from rivers and reservoirs because of this,
and mushroom habitats have been destroyed.
Anyway, a word of advice on storing mushrooms.
Collect them in a brown paper bag and as soon as you get home,
put them in the fridge.
They’ll be fine for a couple of days,
but it’s best to cook them as soon as possible – after washing them
really carefully first, of course.
So everybody knows what a mushroom tastes like, right?
Well, you’ll be surprised by the huge variety of wild mushrooms there are.
Be adventurous!
They’re great in so many dishes – stir fries, risottos, pasta.
But just be aware that some people can react badly to certain varieties
so it’s a good idea not to eat huge quantities to begin with.
OK,
so now I’m going to show you …